We propose a tongue-in-cheek quantum-mechanical model of romantic relationships in
which the “coordinate” is an abstract attachment strength r and the interaction is described
by the Morse potential. Our Morse formulation is elegant because it achieves maximal
physical content with minimal parameters while remaining exactly solvable in
quantum mechanics—a remarkably rare and beautiful combination. We show that while
immortal Italian poets struggled to understand human romance, the Morse potential’s finite
number of bound states and the clean separation between eternally bound (until death) and
rapidly decaying states reproduce the observed mixture of near-Gaussian lifetimes for viable
couples and heavy-tailed (Pareto-like) lifetimes for non-viable ones surprisingly well. Thus,
Morse’s crystal-precise formulation prevails over Petrarch-inspired renditions in words and
provides a natural second-quantization layer for Rinaldi’s classical love equations. Fake but
credible numerical examples for a high-chemistry and a low-chemistry couple are presented.
